长城名列人类文明的壮举之一 千年来屹立不倒
THE GREAT WALL HAS STOOD FOR CENTURIES AS ONE OF MANKIND'S MOST ENDURING WONDERS.
它绵延五千五百英里 历经一千七百多年修建完成
IT SPANS OVER 5500 MILES AND TOOK MORE THAN 1700 YEARS TO BUILD.
它防御着形形色色的敌人 有真实的故事 也有传说
IT PROTECTED FROM MANY DANGERS. SOME ARE KNOWN. SOME ARE LEGEND.
这就是其中的一则传说
THIS IS ONE OF THE LEGENDS.
片名：长城
THE GREAT WALL
纳吉 把马放开!
Najid, cut the horses loose!
我们得掉头回去
We have to turn back.
都走了六个月了
We have been riding for six months.
我们都死了二十几个人了 还没死光呢
-And we've lost twenty men. -But we survived.
对 快死光了!
Yes. By chance.
下一个死的就该轮到我们了
Any one of us could have met that same fate.
我们几个是最棒的 记住我们来的目的
We were the strongest. Remember why you're here.
要照以前 你敢这么说 我早把你给弄死了
In the West, we would be enemies, and I wouldd have to kill you.
好在我们的目标一致
At least here we have a common goal.
对 黑火药
Oh, yes. This black powder.
它能把空气变成火焰 一次就能干掉十几个人
It turns air into fire. And kills a dozen men at one time.
这是我梦寐以求的武器 那要只是个传说呢?
-It is a weapon of our dreams. -What if it's just a myth?
有人发誓说千真万确
Men have sent word that it's real.
那些人都死了
And those men are dead.
现在该轮到我们了
And we are next.
没有地图
We have no maps,
没有药品
no medicines,
没有吃的
and no food.
不行 谁都不能回去
No one is going back.
我们先清点一下剩下的东西
We take inventory of what we have left
干完这一票再说
and finish what we started.
没啥可用的
There's not much here.
月色很好 等马吃饱了我们就走
The moon is strong. When the horse are fresh, we move.
去哪儿? 往北
-To where? -North.
契丹人如果追上来，就在山里干掉他们
If they keep after us, we'll kill them in the mountains.
一块磁石
The magnet.
太沉了
Too heavy.
留着 没啥用
-Useless. -I'll have it.
你自己拿着
It's all yours.
哥们 你要背块破石头过沙漠啊?
Amigo, only you would carry a stupid magnet through the desert.
我能用它做个指南针
I can use it to make a compass.
里泽蒂不行了
Rizzeti won't make it.
他伤得很重
The wound is festering.
咱们现在等于是在拖着一具尸体在走 我听见了!
-We'll be dragging a corpse. -I heard that.
死在哪儿是他的选择
He's earned the right to die where he wants.
我也被人扔下过两次
I've been left for dead twice.
那些扔下我的人
The people who left me.
他们去哪了?
Where are they?
是契丹人?
Hill tribes?
不是人类
It's no man.
那是什么?
Then what is it?
不管是什么
Whatever it is...
它在捕食
it's hunting.
什么东西? 不知道
-What was that? -I don't know.
我砍了它的爪子
I took its hand.
那……那我们现在……
We need to move.
赶紧走
Agreed.
得带上这个
I'll take the hands with us.
带它干嘛?
What the hell for?
得弄清楚它是什么东西
So someone can tell me what I just killed.
这帮孙子还真是锲而不舍啊
Persistent bastards, aren't they?
我们上山去 居高临下打
We'll take the rise, make a stand there.
人要死了还得兜个风
What a long shitting way to go to die.
这下完了
Mother of God.
放箭!
Fire!
这回去也是死
I have no need to go down fighting.
没错
Agreed.
跟前面的绅士们碰碰运气吧
I say we take our chanches with the gents in front of us.
我可很久没有投降过了
I haven't surrendered in a while, eh.
那就再来一次
It'll come back to you.
只要你听我的 保证平安无事
Follow my lead. We'll be fine.
当然得听你的
Of course, my friend.
咱们是朋友嘛
Where you go, I follow.
都这样了 还能平安无事?
You're doing such a great job already.
传鹿军邓将军
All commanders to the great hall!
传鹤军林将军
All commanders report to the General!
闪开
Make way! Make way!
急传鹤军林将军
All commanders to the large hall!
闪开
Make way!
传鹿军邓将军
Commander Lin is needed immediately!
急传鹤军林将军
Calling Commander Lin!
邵殿帅急传林将军
Commander Lin is needed immediately!
他们对那个感兴趣
They know what it is.
而且表情十分凝重
And they don't look so happy to see it.
必须得找个机会杀出去
All the more reason to get the hell out of here.
我们的武器在桌子上
Our weapons are on that table.
你确定你没疯?
Have you lost your mind?
我只要拿到了弓箭就能干掉这些士兵
I can take the guards on the perimeter with my bow.
你去干掉那几个当官的
You cut the legs out from under the officers.
你真具有非凡的想象力
I must confess this is not my favorite plan.
这是在哪捡的?
Where was this found?
你会说英文?
You speak English.
这下热闹了
Fantastic.
我问你在哪儿捡的?
Where was this found?
不是捡的
It wasn't found.
是我砍的
It was taken.
之前它杀了我们三个人
That thing killed three men before we took it down.
在哪儿?
Where?
骑马往北 两天
Two days ride.
山里
North, in the mountains.
他说在北山 据此两日行程
He says two days ride north, in the mountains.
他自称曾斩杀一头饕餮 两日?
-They claim to have killed it. -Two days?
比我们预计的时间提前了
Earlier than we expected.
王军师
Strategist Wang!
殿帅 我在听
I'm listening, General.
是他们杀的?
The two of them killed it?
你们两个 一起杀的? 那个……我们……
-Two of you, you did this? -Well...
是我杀的 你一个人?
-I killed it. -Alone?
他说是他一个人杀的 他一个人?
-He claims to have killed it alone. -By himself?
怎么可能?
Impossible.
你是怎么杀的?
Tell me how.
就那么一砍一劈
A swing of the sword.
它爪子断了
The hand came away clean.
身体向后一倒 掉进山谷里了
The beast fell back into a chasm.
你们来这儿干什么? 我们是商人
-Why are you here? -We came to trade.
遇上了埋伏
We were ambushed.
来人!
Guards!
你们是军人
You are soldiers.
林将军
Commander Lin.
不可
Wait.
殿帅 他们谎称是遭遇契丹人伏击的商人
They claim to be traders who were ambushed.
这蛮夷真能吹牛
These barbarians are liars.
未必
Perhaps not.
有饕餮断掌为证
They brought the claw here.
刀剑切口一目了然
The wound is fresh.
在他们的剑和衣服上都有绿血
There is green blood on his sword.
完全有那个可能
Those prove his story.
末将以为 无论巧合与否 应立即处死二人
To protect our secret, we must kill them.
以防后患 林将军说的是
-Eliminate the possibility of trouble. -I agree.
砍了算了
We should kill them!
殿帅
General.
他们来历尚未查明
Until we find the truth,
我看还是多留几天吧 报!
-I advise we keep them alive. -Alert!
启禀殿帅大人 烽火台狼烟四起
General, signals from the smoke towers!
有敌来犯!
We are under attack!
先将俘虏押至北楼
Take them to the stockade.
传今全体将士 准备迎战 是 准备迎敌!
-All stations on full alert! -Yes! All stations on full alert!
小娘子 你真要处决我们吗?
Are you killing us, Sister?
我们两只可怜的迷途羔羊?
Two lost travelers?
这到底是怎么回事啊?
What's happening here?
你不是保证平安无事的吗?
Is this bitch going to kill us?
先别这么紧张
I think she'd like that.
真要杀我们啊? 亲
If it is death, my dear,
你下得了手吗
we need time to pray.
我得跟她套套近乎
I'm trying here.
小娘子 我知道你们被围攻了
Sister, I know a siege when I see one.
可是你们城墙这么高 不用担心的
What comes at you so hard you need a wall like this?
我砍的到底是什么东西? 饕餮
-What the hell did we kill out there? -Tao Tei.
你杀了一只饕餮侦察兵
You killed a Tao Tei scout.
就凭你一个人
You killed it alone.
和我们预想的一样 大战将至
You are correct. We are under siege.
只是它们的攻击提前了九天
But we did not expect the attack for another nine days.
攻击?
Attack?
饕餮到底是什么东西?
-Tao Tei? -What the hell is a Tao Tei?
你们的经历很重要
Many things about your story have importance.
所以先让你们活着
You are not to die today.
快!
Hurry!
启禀军师 钥…钥匙找不着了
I'm sorry, sir. I can not find the key.
算了!
Forget it!
带他们上城 交熊军临时看押
Bring them to the wall. Keep an eye on them!
殿帅
General.
终于来了
It's finally happening.
是啊
Yes.
这一仗等了六十年
60 years preparing for this moment.
站住!
Stop! Stop!
进去!
Go. Go!
Inside!
进去!
Stand still!
坐下!
Get down! Get down!
黑色的应该是步兵
The black are the foot soldiers.
红的呢? 红的是弓弩手
-And the red? -Those are the archers.
这蓝色的是? 都是女人
-And the blue? -They're all women.
女人来搞什么?
What the hell do they do?
装备精良
Look at this army.
你见过这样的军队吗? 真牛
-Have you ever seen anything like this? -Incredible.
接枪
Catch it!
他们看起来很紧张
They look nervous.
墙这么高 他们到底紧张什么啊?
It's a big wall to be so nervous.
怎么听着不对劲儿啊
Do you hear it?
远攻! 是 战鼓队传令远攻!
-Long distance weapons! -Yes! Drums signal long distance weapons!
扶好!
Grab it!
点火!
Light it!
对准腋下之目!
Aim for the eyes! Aim for the eyes!
飞索攻击!
Crane Corps attack!
威廉 你看那儿
William, over there.
他怎么没被绑着?
Why isn't he tied up?
我们有机会了
There's our escape.
殿帅 那应该是兽王 它在指挥
General. There's the queen. She commands them.
攻击兽王!
Attack the queen!
近战! 是 近战!
-Close combat! -Yes! Close combat!
战鼓队传令近战!
Drums signal close combat.
我们得离开! 要不然我们就死定了!
We need to move! We need to move or we die!
上 上
Go, go!
上去打它呀
Go and fight!
快帮我解开
Cut me loose!
打还是逃? 往哪儿逃啊?
-Fight or run? -Run where?
射它们的眼睛
Aim for the eyes!
威廉
William!
畜生 来啊
Hey! Bitch!
威廉 我需要个角度
-William. -I need a shot.
什么神造出了这些怪物?
What god made those things?
反正不是我们的神
None that we know.
他们还会处死我们吗? 那倒省事儿了
-Think they'll hang us now? -I could use the rest.
听说今天打得不错 我们殿帅在夸奖你们
-You fought well today. -You've earned General Shao's praise.
它们还会回来吗? 会的
-Will they come back? -Yes.
我们得随时准备好
All we can do is prepare.
带他们回营房
Take them to the barracks.
给他们准备一个房间 是!
-They need rest. -Yes!
感谢救命之恩
Thank you for saving my life.
林将军
Commander Lin.
你从小在禁军中长大
You grew up in the Nameless Order.
我也教会了你很多东西
I've taught you many things,
你也在不断地学习
and you have been learning,
但是它们也在学习
but they have been learning also.
王军师说过它们在变化
Strategist Wang warned they are evolving.
我们没有认真听
No one listened.
我们今天面对的对手
The enemies we're facing today
己经不是六十年前的敌人了
are more intelligent than 60 years ago.
盯紧那两个外邦
Watch the foreigners closely.
姑且好生款待
They can never leave.
一旦查明实情 立即处死 遵命
-We must protect the secrets of the Wall. -Yes sir!
你是谁啊?
Who are you?
等一下
Easy.
我叫巴拉德
I'm Ballard.
我叫威廉
William.
这是托瓦尔
This is Tovar.
你们来干什么?
What are you doing here?
当然为了黑火药 果然如我所料
-We came looking for black powder. -I bet you did.
二十五年前 我随一队雇佣兵来到这儿
I came with merceneries for the same thing,
也是为了这个
25 years ago.
你找到了吗?
And did you find it?
找到了和活着带出去可是两回事
Finding it and leaving with it alive are two different things.
不过 你们参加了战斗 就等于是先下了步好棋
You saved the west turret. That was extremely diplomatic.
杀死怪兽不是下棋
We weren't being diplomatic.
是为了保命
We were trying to stay alive.
你们闻起来跟牲畜一样臭 多谢
-You smell like animals. -Thank you.
洗干净 会给你们饭吃
Clean up and they'll feed you.
他知道黑火药在哪儿
He knows where the powder is.
那他怎么还在这儿?
Then why is he still here?
他需要我们当帮手
He needs help getting out?
有可能
Right.
拿到火药 就回家
We play our part, take the powder and go home.
你好像漏了件大事 什么大事?
-I didn't sign up for this. -Which part?
所有事 主要是怪兽
Well... All of it. But mostly the monsters.
好多怪兽
There's a lot of them.
我们真的很臭
We really do smell.
我们邵殿帅感谢你们参加战斗
General Shao welcomes you as honored guests of the Nameless Order,
并赞赏你们勇气可嘉
and thanks you for your skill and courage.
我们感谢你们的感谢
We are honored to be honored.
话都不会说了?
Is that the best you've got?
殿帅
General.
我们见过他的兵器
I couldn't help wondering,
想不通像他这样一位神箭手
why would such an accomplished archer
为何会用这样一张破弓?
used such a primitive bow.
陈将军认为 你的弓跟你的身手不相配
Commander Chen thinks your bow is not worthy of your skill.
告诉他 这张弓无与伦比
Tell him there's no better weapon here.
他说 这张弓全城独一无二
He claims his weapon is second to none.
请他给我们展示一下 让将士们开开眼
Let him show us. Give him some space!
大家想领教一下 在这?
-They wish to see you shoot. -In here?
众目睽睽 要是为难 就算了
Unless he's afraid. It's a large audience.
什么意思? 他说当着这么多人
-What was that? -He thinks you have fear.
你怕出丑
Too many people.
你拿一只碗来 真来呀?
-Get one of the cups. -Now?
去拿只碗来 我都快饿死了
-Get one of the cups. -I want to eat.
照老样子 上次你可演砸了
You remember how to do this? Last Time didn't go so good.
那是喝大了
-We were drunk. -How high?
多高? 十码吧 向右 六掌
10 yards. Six hands to the right.
行不行啊 没事 就这么来
-Turn around. -No. I'll do it this way.
一
One.
二
Two.
三
Three.
扔
Pull.
臭美够了吧 我可得开吃了
Good luck with that. I want food.
谁教你的英语? 巴拉德教我的
-Who taught you English? -Sir Ballard.
英文和拉丁文
English and Latin.
听说他在这儿已经二十五年了
Heard he's been here for twenty five years.
你们一直扣留他
You won't let him leave.
他必须留下
He must stay here.
那我们昵?
What about us?
悠着点吃 一顿都少不了你的
Pace yourself. The meals are regular here.
我可没想像你一样待那么久
I hope not to stay that long.
这么想就对了
I like your thinking,
我劝你还是别让人看出来你想干嘛
but I suggest you keep your plans private.
你们不是唯一为了黑火药而来的西方人
You aren't the first Westerners to come here looking for black powder.
你们今晚来我房间 商量一下
We'll discuss it tonight. Bring your partner.
你在这儿多久了? 一直都在
-How long have you been here? -Always.
我不到五岁就来这儿了
I was not five years old when I came here.
我从小就没有家人
I have no other family.
那咱们是同类人
We're the same.
我也是被军队收养的 在我记事之前
I was given to an army before I can remember.
当了士兵? 比那还遭 一名打扫
-As a soldier? -Worse. As a gleaner.
就是一群孩子 在战斗结束之后
Packs of children, we'd clean the battlefields.
负责打扫战场 后来成了待卫
After, when the fighting's over, I became a page.
一名长矛兵 为了你的国家吗?
-a pikeman's boy. -For Your country?
不 为了填饱肚子
No. I fought for food.
为了生存
You fight to eat.
也是为了钱而战
You live long enough, you fight for money.
你可以为多少国家卖命?
How many flag do you fight for?
我不确定
I don't know.
我帮哈罗德打丹麦人
I fought for Harold against the Danes.
救了公爵的命 他死之前我一直为他打仗
I saved a Duke's life. I fought for him until he died.
我帮西班牙人打法兰克人
Fought for Spain against the Franks.
又帮法兰克人打布伦人
Fought for Franks against Boulogne.
还为教皇打过仗
I fought for the Pope.
很多国家
Many flags.
我们并不是同类人
We are not the same.
来城墙上找我 让你见识一下
Meet me on the Wall. I have something to show you.
这个女人你得防着点儿
He should be careful with her.
她可不是省油的灯
She's very powerful here.
正好 我们也不省油
Then it is a fair contest.
上来
Come.
敢不敢试试?
You wish to try?
男人那么重 拉得上来吗?
Men are too heavy. Do you think we can pull him up?
她说男人可以做很好的示范
She says men have so much to teach us.
我觉得她说的不是这个意思
I don't think that's what she said.
我看出来了
You know what I think?
你又怯场了
I think you're afraid.
刚才射箭前你也这么说
You said that this morning.
我这不是……
And yet,
来了吗?
here I am.
好啊
Yes.
那来吧
Here you are.
你是跳…… 还是不跳?
Will you jump? Or not?
他们靠的住吗? 这你不用操心
-These men know what they're doing? -Wrong question.
你该操心的是 你身上的绳子绑好了没有
Whether or not the cable is attached, that is the question.
关键是什么呢?
-And the answer? -Xin ren.
信任
Xin ren?
信任 彼此之间 相信
Xin ren means trust. To have faith.
我们这支军队 不为钱和食物而战
Here, in this army, we fight for more than food or money.
我们的牺牲更有意义
We give our lives to something more.
我们以信任为旗帜 彼此支持 彼此信任
Xin ren is our flag. Trust in each other.
不论何时 不论何地
In all ways, at all times.
你说的有道理 但我是不会跳
Well, that's all well and good, but I'm not jumping.
我能活到今天 就是因为我只相信自己
A man must learn to trust, before he can be trusted.
其实 你信任别人 就是相信自己
你说的对
Then you were right.
我们并不是同类人
We're not the same.
快 下次袭击随时开始!
Stay vigilant! The next attack is coming!
天呐
My god!
让你们先开开眼
A taste, a glimpse,
这点黑火药
a few pilfered grains
还是我从王军师那儿偷偷弄来的
from Strategist Wang's supply of black powder.
很珍贵
王军师这个人 对黑火药可是很有研究
He's mastered the transmutation of these elements.
据说有种火药武器
People speak of a weapon.
这里的武器五花八门
There are many weapons here.
我怎么没见到呀
Why have we not seen them?
你没见过的东西多着呢
There are many things you have not seen.
你应该祷告 最好别在战斗中用上它
And many things you should pray
否则你就玩儿完了
will not be needed before the siege is through.
饕餮还会回来的
The Tao Tei will return.
当战鼓响起的时候
When the drums call to battle,
全体将士上城墙各就各位
the guards leave their post and take their positions on the Wall.
那就是我们逃跑的机会
That is our moment.
只要他们一打起来…… 我们就开溜
We want to be riding away as the battle rages.
那火药仓库的门呢?
And the armory doors?
有钥匙吗? 黑火药我这还有
-You have keys? -I have black powder,
够炸开好几道门了
enough for several doors.
我们互相协作 各取所需 离开这儿
He brings us in. We get us out.
王军师有请诸位
Strategist Wang request your presence.
你搏斗时 这块石头在哪?
As you fought, where was this stone?
在我包里
In my bag.
真是无形的力量
Its unseen force is powerfull.
看来得好好研究一下这块石头
I believe this strange stone could help us.
玄机何在
We try everything.
饕餮现在在哪? 钩吾山 准备下一次的攻击
-Where are the Tao Tei now? -The mountains, regrouping.
它们从哪来的?
Where do they come from?
在大约两千年以前
About 20 centuries ago,
有一位皇帝 贪婪无度 令民不聊生
There was an emperor whose greed brought deep suffering to all of China.
激怒上苍 天降陨石击中钩吾山
The heaven sent a meteor that struck Gouwu Mountain
绿光中释放出饕餮
turning it green and releasing Tao Tei.
从此在中国北方的土地上 六十年一个轮回
From that day on, the Tao Tei rise every sixty years,
几经饕餮的肆虐
to scourge the north of China.
以此告诫世人 贪婪的后果
They come to remind us of what happens when greed is unchecked.
饕餮兵兽见人就吃 无论死活
They eat anything, alive or dead,
只是为了去填饱兽王的肚皮 饕餮兽王不捕食 全靠兵兽喂养它
and take food to their queen. She depends on her soldiers to feed her.
她吃饱了就会大量的繁殖
Only with the food they provide is she able to multiply.
离长城八百里外的汴梁 那里有两百万的人口
The capital and its 2 million people, is only 800 li away.
如果这两百万人变成它们充足的食物
If the Tao Tei ever had that much nourisment
那么天下将永无宁日
no corner of the world would be safe.
为什么不去杀了它们? 当然试过 他们去了
-You can't hunt them? -Men try. They disappear.
一个也没回来
We never find their bones.
邵殿帅紧急巡查西箭楼!
Troops unaccounted for at the West Tower!
它们为何丢下尸体?
Why did they leave the bodies?
下马!
Dismount!
建阵!
Formation!
前进!
Advance!
停一下
Stop.
林将军
Commander Lin.
殿帅
General...
它们又进步了
They led us into a trap.
懂得偷袭我们的要害了
We underestimated their intelligence.
禁军……
The Nameless Order...
就交给你了 殿帅
-is yours to command. -General...
众将军听令……
Commanders, this is my final order...
从今天起
from this day forward,
林将军就是你们的殿帅
Commander Lin will lead you.
禁军全体将士 愿接受林将军的率领
The soldiers of the Nameless Order will stand firm.
保家卫国 誓灭饕餮!
The wall must not fall! We will defeat the Tao Tei!
请殿帅放心!
-Rest in peace. -Rest in peace!
秦时明月汉时关
万里长征人未还
但使龙城飞将在
不教胡马度阴山
枢密院特使沈大人
This is envoy Shen from the palace.
他特地从汴梁带来史料 协助我们对付饕餮
He has brought important records to help with the coming battle.
据九百多年前史料记载 九百年前的史料上写道
-This is a 900 years old batte report. -A 900 years old battle report.
当年在寒沙门 有三只饕餮爬上了城楼
At the Hans Gate, three beasts mounted the wall.
越过城楼 沿途杀了很多人
They killed many men as they went forward.
但是 也许是上天的力量
Then, by the grace of the ancient gods,
饕餮突然停了下来
the beasts stopped
静止不动了 士兵上前将其斩杀
and sat peacefully, as we slaughtered them.
当时现场有一块磁石 跟这一块一样
There was a magnet on site just like this one.
当年在寒沙门 也有一块像这样的磁石
At the Hans Gate, was a magnet just like this one.
他说是因为你身上的这块磁石
I believe that magnet was the reason the two of you Westerners
你才能轻而易举地把那只饕餮杀死了
killed the Tao Tei so easily.
他觉得是磁石 让饕餮的耳朵聋了
I believe the magnet makes the Tao Tei deaf.
饕餮听不到兽王的指令就静止了
Without instruction, they fall still.
此事如何验证? 怎么确定?
-How to prove that? -How can we be sure?
试试就行
Why not try it?
抓一只饕餮
Capture a Tao Tei. See if it works.
测试一下 他说他要尝试一下 就得抓一只 怎么抓?
-He wants to try. He wants to catch one. -How?
根本没有那么结实的网
No net is strong enough.
直接抓 就像捕鲸一样 你知道我在说什么
Hunt them. Like a whale. You know what that is.
那是一种水里的巨兽 可比饕餮大百倍
A water beast. A hundred times the size of a Tao Tei.
用带勾的叉勾住它的骨头 用有钩的鱼叉 直接就可以把它抓住
A spear that grabs. Hook the bone.
我在西班牙见过
I've seen it done in Spain.
他说的也许是个办法
He claims to have seen it done in Spain.
你跟着瞎搅合什么?
What the hell are you doing?
只要他们打起来我们就得逃
We need to be free when the attack comes.
这可是唯一的机会
How many chances do you think we will get?
装受伤 玩失踪 做个胆小鬼行吗?
Be injured. Be missing. Be a coward.
别再瞎掺和了
Get out of this.
我们已经够意思了
We did enough.
你们要调稠一点 才能麻醉它
The mixture must be strong to put the creature to sleep.
把麻药涂匀了 是!
-Spread it on evenly. -Yes, Commander!
楞什么?
Snap out of it!
给我滚到伙房去 不要再上来!
Useless idiot! report to the kitchen where you belong!
遵命 滚!
-Yes, Commander. -Go!
他会来的 什么时候? 等打完仗?
-He'll be here. -When? When it was over?
那我们边干边等 边干边等?
-We will start and he will find us. -Start?
开弓没有回头箭 我一切都准备好了
We're jumping off a cliff here. I have everything.
火药 工具 地图
Powder, tools, maps.
都藏好在逃跑的沿途
It's all hidden and arranged along the route.
一旦动手 毫无退路
Once we start, there's no going back.
敢死队 上 是 敢死队上
-Death Squad ready! -Yes! Death Squad go!
大刀准备!
Blades ready!
大刀起!
Blades forward!
攻击!
-Attack! -Go!
左! 右!
Left! Right!
我去找他 甭管他了
-I'll find him. -Forget him.
他现在一心只想着讨好那个女殿帅
He'd rather die trying to impress the new general
你说等拿到火药有了钱 什么妞不能玩啊?
than grab the key to every counting room and brothel in the world.
不能再等了 现在就得行动 不能扔下他
Good God, man. The time is now. I can't go without him.
少一个人分钱不是更好 我们需要他的弓
-More the spoils for us! -We need his bow!
鱼叉箭 放!
Harpoons, Now!
是 鱼叉箭放!
Yes! Harpoons, fire!
齐放
Fire!
最后一根了! 让开!
-Move! -It's the last one!
再拉! 停一下!
-Pull! -No, no, no. Stop!
你们拉得太紧 链子会断的
There's too much tension! Chain will break.
先松一下 让它先拉
-That way. That way. -Let him run!
停 我们得等一会儿 让麻药起作用
Stop! Stop! We need longer for the sleeping potion to work.
拉 拉起来
That way. That way.
得想办法挡开其他饕餮
We need to isolate it. Sparate it from the others.
火球保护! 是 火球保护!
-Ring of Fire! -Yes! Ring of Fire!
铁链要断了! 不好啦!
-The chain won't hold much longer! -We're losing him!
威廉 等等 响箭! 是 响箭!
-William, wait. Screaming arrows! -Yes! Screaming arrows!
中了响箭的饕餮 一跑就会响
These arrows will scream as the Tao Tei run.
瞄准声音射箭
Aim for the sound.
火球圈内 响箭覆盖!
Aim inside the circle. Blanket the whole area.
放!
Fire!
收!
Pull!
救你一命 是因为我想亲手宰了你
I'm only saving you so I can kill you myself.
捡把斧头 盲打
Grab the axe, we're fighting blind.
可能现在做不是…… 你少废话
-Not yet! -I know what to do!
火焰挡不住它们了 那就永别吧 兄弟
-The fire is not holding them back here. -Die well, brother.
你在干嘛? 给她发信号!
-What the hell are you doing? -She's listening.
火药箭 霹雳弹准备! 是 火药箭霹雳弹准备!
-Prepare black powder weapon! -Prepare black powder weapon!
佩戴火绳
Prepare to light the fuses!
是 佩戴火绳!
Yes! Prepare to light the fuses!
成功了吗? 是的
-Did it work? -Yes.
抓了个活的
The beast was captured.
那我朋友呢? 放心 他没事
-My friend... -He was unharmed.
你为什么要跳下去?
Why did you go over the Wall?
信任 我说的对吗?
Xin ren. Did I say that right?
谢谢你
Thank you.
我们的黑火药
Black powder.
这是一种可怕的武器
It is a terrible weapon.
我真希望你 不曾见过
It would be better if you had never see it.
我对外面的世界 了解的并不是很多
I know very little of the outside world.
在我看来 人类与饕餮的贪婪并无区别
But it seems to me, the greed of men is not that different than the Tao Tei.
我说的对吗?
Is that true?
弱肉强食
The strong take what they want.
忘掉你所看到的一切
Forget what you have seen.
好! 即刻押送沐梁
Excellent! Send it to the capital immediately.
不可! 需就地研究
No! We need to study it here.
饕餮若能活捉 皇上必须先睹
If a Tao Tei is captured alive, it must be sent to the emperor.
下官特地为此事而来 这可是皇上的旨意
This is an Imperial Order.
你比你想象中的要勇敢得多
You're much braver than they think.
没受伤吧?
You're wounded?
刚才我在找你
I was looking for you.
是想说谢谢你
To say thank you.
你感觉很好吧? 想不想唱两句啊?
You feel good, huh? Maybe you sing a little song, eh?
要不一块儿唱
I will join you.
歌唱一个伟大的英雄拯救了中国人
We can sing together how you saved the gratefull Chinos.
干嘛这么说 你目睹了一切
You saw what happened out there, and that's what you say?
我看到了黑火药
I see black powder.
也看到你忘了朋友 放心吧 黑火药又不会跑……
-I see a man forget his friends. -The black powder's not going anywhere.
我看不会跑的是你
What goes nowhere is you.
你永远都得不到你想要的
You'll never get what you want from this.
你以为他们拿你当英雄吗?
You think they see you as some kind of hero?
或是救世主? 你骗得了他们
A man of virtue? Maybe you can fool them,
但骗不了我
but I know what you are.
你自己心里也清楚
You know what you are.
你就是个贼 谎言家
A thief, a liar,
是个杀手
and a killer.
还想放下屠刀 立地成佛
You can never undo things you've done.
狗改不了吃屎
and you will never be anything.
这才像是我的哥们儿
Good to see you again, amigo.
发现饕餮! 发现饕餮! 发现饕餮!
Tao Tei movement!
全体上城!
All troops to the Wall!
又没影了?
-Nothing? -No.
你肯定他不会出卖我们? 不会的
-How do you know he won't betray us? -I don't.
他们会杀了他 不管怎样都会
They'll kill him. They'll kill him no matter what.
他们杀他的时候
The time they spend killing him,
我们已经带上东西跑远了
is time they are not chasing us.
小心点 这可有黑火药
Careful with that. There's powder here.
托瓦尔
Tovar.
殿帅 打通了! 饕餮已突破长城!
General, it goes all the way through. Tao Tei have breached the wall.
它们居然如此狡猾
They're smarter than we thought.
传令所有将军 立即来此! 遵命!
-Summon my commanders immediately! -Yes, General!
去看看 是不是灭了
Have a look. See if it's gone out.
安全吗? 当然了
-Is it safe? -Of course it is.
醒醒 开工了
Shake it off, man. To work.
安全个屁 差点要了我的命
I thought you said it was safe?
结果还是不错的
We're in, didn't we?
你来了 终于醒悟了啊?
-You're here. -We've come to our senses, eh?
他的计划很周密 逃出去并不难
Ballard has planned well. Getting out is easy.
从这走往西二十英里后出长城 只要我们能避开契丹人
There's a gate. 20 miles west. We dodge the hill tribes.
那就大功告成了 这里需要我们
-We can make it. -They need us here.
需要的人多了
They need more than us.
留下来就是死路一条 别犯傻了
-These people are doomed. -Don't be a fool.
我过去才是犯傻
I've been a fool.
现在不会了
I'm done with it.
哥们 求你了
Brother, please.
过去的战斗毫无意义
We've been fighting for nothing.
只是为了贪婪
For greed.
听我说哥们儿 咱们历尽干辛万苦 九死一生
Amigo, after all the blood, the cold, and pain,
好不容易有了这黑火药 目的达到了
with this black powder in our saddle bags, we win.
跟我们一起走吧
You come with me.
我不能那么做
I can't do that now.
留下来跟我一起战斗 威廉
-Stay and fight. -William...
他死了吗? 没那么容易
-Think he's dead? -It'd take a lot more than that.
没想到它们前两次都是佯攻 我们都上当了
All of the attacks have been a diversion, while they dug this tunnel.
过了长城
They have breached the wall.
汴梁有它们无穷无尽的食物 后果不堪设想
Once they reach the capital, nothing in the world can stop them.
我的骑兵就算是快马加鞭 也得两天才能到汴梁
At a full gallop, it's two days to the capital.
它们肯定比我们快 现在风很强
-There's no way we can catch them. -The wind is strong now.
明天一整天吹北风 我们必须启用新发明
It blows from the north all day tomorrow. We have to use the balloons.
到汴梁要多久? 顺风约三个时辰 三个时辰
-If it works, how long to Bianliang? -Six hours if the wind hold.
如果能活着的话
If we make it alive.
殿帅 这些东西从没试过
General, none of the tests have worked.
准备出发!
Get ready!
走吧
Come on!
都城汴梁
THE CAPITAL BIANLIANG
怎么抓的? 启禀皇上……
-How did you capture it? -Your Excellency!
皇上 是那块磁石 能制住这畜生
Your Excellency, It's the magnet. It keeps the beast under control.
自饕餮成祸以来 此发现最为重大
This is the most important discovery in the history of the Tao Tei.
枢密院将立即展开研究 把他拉下来!
-We will investigate immediately. -Bring him here!
我试着…… 你还敢狡辩?
-I tried to stop... -You dare to speak to me?
这事不是我干的 是啊 你是一个商人
-I didn't do this. -And you came here to trade.
你不是为了黑火药而来
And you knew nothing of black powder.
你一定觉得我是个傻子是吧
What a fool you must think I am.
如果我是同伙 我还会在这吗?
If I was with them, why would I be here? I tried to stop them.
骗子!
Liar!
你是个骗子
You lie.
你心里知道 不是这样的 如果我不是殿帅
-Some part of you knows that's not true. -If I were not the General,
我会亲手杀了你
I would kill you myself.
殿帅!
General!
启禀殿帅…… 大声点!
-General. -Speak up.
事发时小人正在翰渊阁 小人亲眼看见他阻拦那两个人
I was there when it happened. I saw him try to stop them.
你确定吗?
Are you sure?
你敢说半句假话 我先铡了你!
If you're lying, I'll have your head!
小人以无影禁军的名誉起誓 所说绝无半句虚言
I swear on my vow to the Nameless Order!
严加看管
Lock him up.
派骑兵队 把那两个盗贼抓回来!
Send the cavalry. Go after the two that got away.
遵命!
Yes, General.
往左还是往右?
Which way, left or right?
得去高处看一下
Go up and take a look from the high ground.
不 混蛋
No! Bastard!
把牢方向! 是 把牢方向!
-Keep it steady! -Yes, General!
小心火药! 是 小心火药!
-Watch the powder! -Yes, General!
出什么事了?
What happened?
怎么了军师? 我们失败了
What happened? We have failed.
饕餮已经越过长城
The Tao Tei are in the kingdom.
你自由了 想要什么都拿上走吧
You are free to leave. Take what you wish and go.
这是殿帅最后的命令 她在哪?
-This was the General's final order. -Where is she?
她去干什么? 战斗?
To do what? To fight?
能赢吗? 只有一种可能
-Is there a chance? -There's only one.
杀死兽王 兽王不死 我们都会死
Kill the Queen. Kill the Queen, or we all die.
你回家吧 讲出你看到的一切
Leave. Tell the world what you have seen,
告诉世人 大难将至
and tell them what is coming.
我的弓在哪儿?
I'll need my bow.
我要和你们一起参加战斗
If I'm to join you, I'll need my bow.
启禀军师! 启禀军师 带上我
Strategist Wang! Please take me with you.
他想和我们一起去
He wishes to join us.
距离不同
The distance is the key.
这畜生的反应也不同
The magnet is only effective when close to the beast.
所以…… 磁石的远近
Therefore, the effect weakens as it gets further away.
才是研究的重点
You see I have it under complete control.
记下了 九尺
Write down nine feet.
往后飞 后殿! 是 后殿!
-Steer to the rear of the palace. -Yes! To the rear of the palace!
上面
Above you!
霹雳弹! 是 霹雳弹!
-Light a grenade! -Yes, sir!
快接着
Behind you!
我让你回家的
I set you free.
可我还是来了
And here I am.
兽王在那儿!
There's the queen!
它们在进食 不会进攻
They will not attack while the queen is feeding.
这是我们的机会 抓紧了!
We have a chance! Hold on!
来者何人?
State your purpose!
无影禁军殿帅林梅 参见皇上!
General Lin Mae from Nameless Order. At your service!
你们怎么回事?
What took you so long?
饕餮都冲到朕的门口了!
The Tao Tei overrun the city!
朕的几千御林军 还有无数的黎民百姓
Thousands of soldiers and innocent are dead.
一眨眼全都没了!
You're too late!
被捕获的那个饕餮现在在哪
Where is the captured Tao Tei?
关地牢了 要利用它杀死兽王
-In the dungeon! -We need it to kill the queen.
兽王死了 信号就断了
Once she is dead, The Tao Tei can not function.
成干上万的饕餮就会僵住无用
Without her signal, their whole army will freeze.
这有一条地下通道
There is an underground canal here.
没有饕餮吗?
Has it been breached?
应该都在地上
The Tao Tei should all be above ground.
我们捕获的那个呢?
And the one we captured?
带上它
We load it up.
喂饱了以后 它会回去找兽王
We feed him. And it will return to its queen.
好
Good.
会留下很酷的伤疤
You'll have one hell of a scar,
不过死不了 他说你会活着
-but you'll live. -He says you will live.
回头再救他
We'll come back for him.
它们攻进来了!
They've broken through!
别轻举妄动 威廉
Patience, William.
你确定它吃饱了会去找兽王?
And it will go to the Queen when it's done?
应该吧
It should.
我确定
It will.
放它进去啊
Let it in.
我能从上面把箭射进去
I can get a shot from above.
上去! 我挡住它们
Go! I'll hold them back.
等等 它接近兽王了
Wait. Not yet.
中
Hit.
再上 它们护不住头顶
Go higher. I'll get a better shot.
殿帅 全靠你们了!
General! It's up to you now!
只剩一件火药武器了 把火药枪给我
We have one black powder weapon left. Give me the spear.
我苦练一生 只为此战
I've trained for this my whole life.
信任
Trust.
我们相互信任
I'll get you the shot.
抓紧我!
I've got you.
没有我的日子如何啊?
So, how's life without me?
有点无聊
A little slow.
听说你是大英雄了 那必须的
-You're a hero after all. -Oh, it looks that way.
瞧你得意那样儿
You seem pleased with yourself..
拯救世界的大英雄有什么奖励?
And what are they giving you for all your troubles?
一袋金子?
A bag of gold?
还是在长城上为你嘉喜庆典?
A victory parade along the top of the Wall?
黑火药我随便拿
All the black powder I can carry.
还有骑兵护送 保护我回家
And a cavalry escort to get me home safely.
那恭喜你了 谢谢
-Well, congratulations. -Thank you.
所以你就
So what is this?
跟我在这显摆? 那当然啦
-You're here to rub my nose in it? -Well, would you blame me?
上次你扔下我一个人等死
The last time I saw you, you left me for dead.
再上一次 我还救了你一命呢
And the time before, I saved your life.
倒也是
True.
其实皇上给了我两个选择
You know, the Emperor gave me a choice.
带走黑火药…… 或者带走你
I could take the black powder or I could take you.
那你可干万别选我
Please tell me you chose the powder.
你让我很失望啊
I don't even know you anymore.
马已备好 日落前我们就可以出发
The horses are saddled and waiting. Best we ride before nightfall.
我先回避下
I'll be inside.
走时还得选我啊
Don't leave without me.
我是来道别的
I came to say goodbye.
听说你荣升骠骑大将军了
I understand congratulations are in order.
我真的很为你感到高兴
General of the northwest territory.
应该祝贺你
Quite an honor.
看来你已经选择好了
Seems you've made your choice.
他啊? 说实话 我真的想用这小子换黑火药来着
Oh, him? Believe me, I'm already think about trading him back for the powder.
我可听着呢
I heard that.
也许 我们都说得不对
Perhaps we were both wrong.
其实我们就是一类人
We are more similar than I thought.
谢谢大将军
Thank you General.
你考虑好了 不想留下来陪她?
-Are you sure you don't want to go back? -Of course I do.
可我怕你一个人回不了家
I just don't trust you to make it out of here alone.